Ellen Gates Starr Papers, 1659-1940
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1659-1975
  - Jane Addams
    - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom tribute, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Lillie family, 1913, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1791-1975
  - Family
    - Starr, Ellen Gates
      - Family
        - Allen, Mary and Frances, 1884-93, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - Blaisdell, Mary Starr, 1860s-1933 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - Starr, Albert and Jeanne, 1901-29, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Starr, Albert Childs, 1926-35 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - Starr, Caleb Allen and Susan Childs Gates Starr, 1885-1915 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Starr, Eliza Allen and Eunice Starr Wellington, 1880-1914 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        - Starr, Josephine, 1903-40 (Box 7, Folder 7-12)
        - Van Patten, Elizabeth Angela Starr, 1916, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Friends and associates
        - Addams, Anna H., 1888 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - Addams, Jane
          - Record book of copies of letters between Ellen Gates Starr and Jane Addams, 1896 (Box 8, Folder 2)
          - 1878-1931 (Box 8, Folder 3-6)
          - Condolence letters to Ellen Gates Starr, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 7)
        - Amyot, Roland, O.S.S., 1934 (Box 8, Folder 8)
        - Birthday (80th) letters, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 9)
        - Branham, Grace, 1927-36 (Box 8, Folder 10)
        - Burchard, Edward L., 1938 (Box 8, Folder 11)
        - Busch, William, 1927-28 (Box 8, Folder 12)
        - Clark, Daniel, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Clark, Eleanor Grace, 1928-39 (Box 9, Folder 2)
        - Cobden-Sanderson, T.J., 1895-1916 (Box 9, Folder 3)
        - Cook, Albert S., 1900-17, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 4)
        - Cutting, David W., 1919 (Box 9, Folder 5)
        - Delano, Frederic, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 6)
        - Doniat, Johanna, 1912-39 (Box 9, Folder 7-9)
        - Duncan, John, 1904-22 (Box 9, Folder 10)
        - Feeney, Leonard, S.J., 1935 (Box 9, Folder 11)
        - Flint, Edith Foster, 1906-39 (Box 9, Folder 12)
        - Hamilton, Alice, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 13)
        - Handly, John, 1922-35 (Box 9, Folder 14)
        - Hickey, James, C.S.P., 1919 (Box 9, Folder 15)
        - Hillman, Sidney, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 16)
        - Huntington, Father James, 1893, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 17)
        - Johnston, Jean, 1905? (Box 9, Folder 18)
        - Kilmer, Aline, 1924 (Box 9, Folder 19)
        - Lillie, Frances Crane, 1906-40 (Box 9, Folder 20-24)
        - Lillie, Frank R., 1924, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 25)
        - Lindin, Mrs. Carl Eric, 1912-40 (Box 9, Folder 26)
        - Linn, James Weber, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 27)
        - McGovern, Dr., 1903 (Box 9, Folder 28)
        - MacLean, Mrs. 1915 (Box 9, Folder 28)
        - MacLeish, Martha H., 1938 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        - Mariotti, Eva, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        - Massa, Helen, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        - Merrill, William Stetson, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 4)
        - Michel, Virgil, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        - Officer, Harvey, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - Paul, Father, OSB, 1932-38 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - Reoch, Jane, 1907-32 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        - Sargent, Daniel, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        - Scholle, Hardinge, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        - Scudder, Vida D., 1915-29 (Box 10, Folder 11)
        - Sedgwick, Mr., 1928 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        - Smothers, Edgar R., 1927-28 (Box 10, Folder 13)
        - Sturgis, Miss, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 14)
        - Thuis, Columbian, OSB, 1935-38 (Box 10, Folder 15)
        - Urie, Caroline, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 16)
        - Vawter, Cora, 1912-39 (Box 10, Folder 17)
        - Wager, Anna, 1921 (Box 11, Folder 1)
        - Wager, Charles H. A.
          - 1906-21 (Box 11, Folder 2-9)
          - 1922-35 (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
        - Walker, Charlton, 1937-38 (Box 12, Folder 6)
        - Wilder, Thornton, 1930-35 (Box 12, Folder 7)
        - Wilmarth, Mary Hawes, 1905-16 (Box 12, Folder 8)
        - Woods, Robert A., 1890-1915 (Box 12, Folder 9)
        - Yeomans, Edward, 1931 (Box 12, Folder 10)
        - Unidentified, 1926-37 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Allen, George, 1874 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Allen, Mary E. and Frances, 1918-37 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Blaisdell, Mary Houghton Starr
      - Family
        - Starr, Josephine, 1911-31 (Box 13, Folder 3-7)
        - Miscellaneous, 1856-1915 (Box 13, Folder 8-9)
      - Friends and associates
        - Addams, Jane, 1914, 1918 (Box 13, Folder 10)
        - Dana, John Cotton, 1898 (Box 13, Folder 11)
        - Kuroda, Kato, 1915 (Box 13, Folder 12)
        - Longfellow, Edith, 1876 (Box 13, Folder 13)
        - Morikichi, 1912 (Box 13, Folder 14)
        - Orcutt, Reginald, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 15)
        - Ranger, H.W., 1909-17 (Box 13, Folder 16)
        - Sawyer, Mary Stebbins, 1865 (Box 13, Folder 17)
        - Toyotaro, 1910-11 (Box 13, Folder 18)
        - Washburn, Rev. A. H., 1865-77 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Gates, Horatio, 1896 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Starr, Albert Childs
      - Family
        - Childs, Susan Gates and Mary H. Starr Blaisdell, 1896, 1913 (Box 14, Folder 2)
        - Starr, Caleb Allen, 1844-1915 (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
        - Starr, Josephine and Eliza A. Starr, 1911-14 (Box 14, Folder 5)
        - Starr, Josephine, 1915-35 (Box 14, Folder 6-7)
    - Starr, Eliza Allen
      - Family, 1845-1901, undated (Box 14, Folder 8-10)
      - Friends and associates
        - Addams, Jane, 1885 (Box 14, Folder 11)
        - Blaisdell, Mary McConnell, 1871-1901 (Box 14, Folder 12)
        - Brownson, Henry F., 1889 (Box 14, Folder 13)
        - Cabrini, M. Francis Xavier, 1900 (Box 14, Folder 14)
        - Davis, Dr. and Mrs. 1880-95 (Box 14, Folder 15)
        - McGovern, Dr. 1895 (Box 14, Folder 16)
        - Miscellaneous, 1875-1900, undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
        - Perkins, Norman, 1877-89 (Box 14, Folder 18-19)
        - Perkins, Robert A., 1884-89 (Box 14, Folder 20)
        - Phillips, Mary Elizabeth, 1895 (Box 14, Folder 21)
        - Sherman, Ellen Ewing, 1886 (Box 14, Folder 22)
        - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Starr, H.L., 1848-49 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Starr, Jeanne Stutz
      - Family
        - Blaisdell, Mary H., 1895-1906 (Box 15, Folder 2)
        - Starr, Josephine, 1912-48 (Box 15, Folder 3)
        - Starr, Josephine and Elizabeth A., 1908 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Starr, Josephine Susanna
      - Family
        - Blaisdell, Mary H. Starr, 1910-18 (Box 15, Folder 5-6)
        - Starr, Albert C., 1912-27 (Box 15, Folder 7)
        - Starr, Jeanne Stutz, 1948-49 (Box 15, Folder 8)
        - Van Patten, Angela Starr, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Friends and associates
        - Addams, Jane, 1930-31 (Box 15, Folder 10)
        - Andrews, Donald H., 1969-72 (Box 15, Folder 11)
        - Chapin, Russell, 1965-66 (Box 15, Folder 12)
        - Collingwood, Ava, 1970-73 (Box 15, Folder 13)
        - Converse, Florence, 1918-20 (Box 15, Folder 14)
        - Conway, Jill Ker, 1964-75 (Box 15, Folder 15)
        - Corwin, Virginia, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 16)
        - Doniat, Johanna, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 17)
        - Flint, Edith Foster, 1918-47 (Box 15, Folder 18)
        - Glenn, Mary W. and John M., 1930-49 (Box 15, Folder 19)
        - Green, Constance McLaughlin, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 20)
        - Head, Lydia Bush-Brown, 1959-74 (Box 15, Folder 21)
        - Hill, Ruth, 1940s-53 (Box 15, Folder 22)
        - Lillie, Frances Crane, 1930-39 (Box 15, Folder 23)
        - MacLeish, Archibald, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 24)
        - McLeod, Rev. George, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 25)
        - Miscellaneous, 1938-71 (Box 15, Folder 26)
        - Orcutt, Reginald, 1911-13 (Box 15, Folder 27)
        - Pabke, Marie Schmiedel, 1924-27 (Box 15, Folder 28)
        - Scales, Laura Lord, 1968-73 (Box 15, Folder 29)
        - Scudder, Vida D., 1918-50 (Box 15, Folder 30)
        - Vawter, Cora, 1940, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 31)
        - Wager, Charles H. A., 1921 (Box 15, Folder 32)
      - About Ellen Gates Starr
        - Arts and Crafts Movement in America, 1972, [see also Judson, The Arts and Crafts Movement in America on shelf] (Box 16, Folder 1)
        - Cobden-Sanderson letters, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Condolence letters on Ellen Gates Starr's death, 1940 (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - Conway, Jill Ker 1964-65 (Box 16, Folder 4)
        - Exhibit at restored Hull House, 1973-74 (Box 16, Folder 5)
        - Sale of Ellen Gates Starr's books
          - Samuel Murray, 1974-75 (Box 16, Folder 6)
          - Newberry Library, 1973-75 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Starr, Lovina Allen, 1857-63, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Starr, Lucy, 1849, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Starr, Oliver, 1845-67 (Box 16, Folder 10-11)
    - Starr, Susan Gates Childs
      - Family, 1863 (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - Blaisdell, Mary H. Starr, 1860, 1900 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Starr, Wesley, 1862 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Starr, William Wesley, 1866-88 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Van Patten, Elizabeth Angela Starr, 1910-29 (Box 16, Folder 16-17)
    - Van Patten, Emerson, 1929-30, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Van Patten, Angela Starr, 1968-71 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Wellington, Charles W. W. and family, 1791-97, 1842-58 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Wellington, Eunice Allen Starr, 1879-1903 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous letters to Starr family, 1818-1905 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Third party
      - Breshkovsky, Catherine, 1910-15 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Doniat, Johanna
        - Clark, Eleanor, 1919 (Box 17, Folder 5)
        - Dewey, Ethel, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 6)
        - Francl, Blanche, 1940 (Box 17, Folder 7)
        - Todd, Arthur J., 1941 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Vawter, Cora, 1918-61 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Wilder, Thorton, 1917-18 (Box 17, Folder 10)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS AND ART WORK 1841-1935
  - Starr, Ellen Gates
    - Bookbinding, 1897-1916, undated, [see also SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS - Miscellaneous] (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Drawings, undated, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Religious
      - Published articles, 1909-37, undated (Box 18, Folder 3-5)
      - Transcripts and notes, 1928, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Notebooks of meditations and notes, 1897-1935, undated (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
      - Christian art, 1906, undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous writings and notes, 1896, undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Notes on The Odyssey, John Ruskin and William Morris, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Blaisdell, Mary Houghton Starr
    - Drawings and art, 1882, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Travel notes and speeches, 1899-1903 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Starr, Eliza Allen
    - Writings on art and religion, 1841-1901, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Lectures and art courses, 1883-97, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Poems and sketches, 1871-1901, undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Poems, Philadelphia, H. McGrath, 1867 (Box 20)
    - Songs Of A Life-Time, Chicago, St. Joseph Cottage, 1887 (Box 20)
    - Pilgrims and Shrines, Chicago, Union Catholic Publishing Co. (2v), 2 copies, 1883 (Box 21)
    - Patron Saints, Baltimore, John B. Piet & Co., 2v (first and second series), 1883 (Box 21)
  - Starr, Jeanne Stutz: lectures on Faust, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Cobden-Sanderson, Thomas J., 1911-16, undated, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 22, Folder 2)
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS 1862-1968
  - Family
    - Starr, Ellen Gates, 1886-1932 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Blaisdell, Charles, undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Blaisdell, Mary Houghton Starr, circa 1851-87 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Starr, Albert Child, 1863-1934 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Starr, Caleb Allen, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Starr, Eliza Allen, undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Starr, Jeanne Stutz and Stutz family, circa 1890, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Starr, Josephine, circa 1898-1968, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Starr, Lavinia and Oliver, 1865 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Starr, Susan Childs, 1862, undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Starr, William Wesley, circa 1862, undated (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Van Patten, Angela Starr, 1951 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Van Patten, Elizabeth Angela, 1907-29 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Wellington, Eunice Allen Starr, undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Friends and associates
    - Jane Addams, 1880-1920, undated (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Cobden-Sanderson family, 1898-99, undated (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1878-88, undated (Box 23, Folder 14-15)
  - Family homes
    - Eliza Allen Starr house, Chicago, n.d (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Conway and Deerfield, MA, Durand, IL 1946, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Book binding, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Ireland photographs by Cora Vawter, 1939 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Albums (Box 25)
    - 1886-1904 (Box 25)
    - 1904-14 (Box 25)
    - 1907-29 (Box 25)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Copy of will for Comfort Starr 1659 (Box 26)
  - Starr, Ellen Gates
    - Flower studies, 1931-32 (Box 26)
    - Drawing of Eliza Allen Starr, undated (Box 26)
  - Cobden-Sanderson, T.J: first sheet from Dove Press, inscribed to Ellen Gates Starr by T.J. Cobden-Sanderson (Box 26)
  - Starr, Josephine: portrait circa 1899 (Box 26)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Carrell, Elizabeth Hutcheson, Reflections In A Mirror: The Progressive Woman And the Settlement Experience. PhD dissertation, University of Texas at Austin. (2v), 1981
  - Clark, Robert Judson, ed. The Arts and Crafts Movement In America, 1876-1916; an exhibition organized by the Art Museum, Princeton University and the Art Institute of Chicago. Princeton, N.J, Princeton University Press, 1972
  - Cook, Albert S., ed. Specimen Letters, Boston, Ginn, 1905
  - Gordon, Anna A., The Beautiful Life of Frances E. Willard, a memorial volume. Chicago, Ill., Women's Temperance Publishing Association, 1898
  - Morgan, Emily Malbone, Letters To Her Companions, ed. by Vida Dutton Scudder, Adelynrood, South Byfield, Mass., Society of the Companions of the Holy Cross, 1944
  - Starr, Eliza Allen, The Life and Letters of Eliza Allen Starr, edited by James J. McGovern, Chicago, Lakeside Press, 1905